<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>-->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<rfc
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      category="bcp"
      consensus="true"
      docName="draft-ietf-mediaman-toplevel-00"
      ipr="trust200902"
      obsoletes=""
      updates="6838"
      submissionType="IETF"
      xml:lang="en"
      tocInclude="true"
      tocDepth="4"
      symRefs="true"
      sortRefs="true"
      version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.38.1 -->
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="New Top Level Media Types">Guidelines for the Definition of New Top Level Media Types</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-mediaman-toplevel-01"/>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->
   <author fullname="Martin J. Dürst" initials="M.J." surname="Dürst">
      <organization>Aoyama Gakuin University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Fuchinobe 5-10-1, Chuo-ku, Sagamihara</street>
          <region>Kanagawa</region>
          <code>252-5258</code>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+81 42 759 6329</phone>
        <email>duerst@it.aoyama.ac.jp</email>
        <uri>https://www.sw.it.aoyama.ac.jp/D%C3%BCrst/</uri>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2022"/>
    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
   <workgroup>MEDIAMAN</workgroup>
    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>Media Type, Top Level</keyword>
    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
      <t>The goal of this document is to identify best practices for defining new top-level media types.
        It updates RFC 6838, when approved.
        Comments and discussion about this document should be directed to media-types@ietf.org,
        the mailing list of the Media Type Maintenance (mediaman) WG.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default"><name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document defines best practices for defining new top-level media types.
        <xref target="RFC6838" format="default">RFC&nbsp;6838</xref> very consisely defines
        the conditions for defining additional top-level media types. This document
        expands this and therefore updates <xref target="RFC6838" format="default">RFC&nbsp;6838</xref>.</t>
      <t>This document is currently a personal draft, but is intended for adoption by the
        Media Type Maintenance (mediaman) IETF WG. Comments and discussion about this document
        should be directed to that WG's mailing list at media-types@ietf.org.</t>
      <t>Currently, this document is a collection of information, ideas, and text snippets
      that may be helpful in creating the actual specification.
      None of the current language is intended to be final.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" format="default">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section><name>Top-Level Media Type History</name>
      <t>This section shortly describes the history of top-level media types, with a particular
      emphasis on the (rather rare) adoption of new top-level types.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC1341" format="default">RFC 1341</xref> first defined the
      structuring of content types into (top-level) type and subtype, and introduced
      the 'text', 'multipart', 'message', 'image', 'audio', 'video', and 'application' top-level types.
      That specification also allowed top-level types starting with 'X-'.
      With respect to new top-level types, it said the following:</t>
      <blockquote>An initial set of seven Content-Types  is  defined  by  this
        document.   This  set  of  top-level names is intended to be
        substantially complete.  It is expected  that  additions  to
        the   larger   set  of  supported  types  can  generally  be
        accomplished by  the  creation  of  new  subtypes  of  these
        initial  types.   In the future, more top-level types may be
        defined only by an extension to this standard.   If  another
        primary  type is to be used for any reason, it must be given
        a name starting  with  "X-"  to  indicate  its  non-standard
        status  and  to  avoid  a  potential  conflict with a future
        official name.</blockquote>
        <t>The first time an additional top-level type was defined was in
          <xref target="RFC1437" format="default">RFC 1437</xref>, but this
          was purely for entertainment purposes (please check date).</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC2046" format="default">RFC 2046</xref> discouraged
      the use of "X-" for (new) top-level types, with the following words:</t>
      <blockquote>In general, the use of "X-" top-level types is strongly discouraged.
        Implementors should invent subtypes of the existing types whenever
        possible. In many cases, a subtype of "application" will be more
        appropriate than a new top-level type.</blockquote>
      <t><xref target="RFC2048" format="default">RFC 2048</xref>, published
        at the same time as <xref target="RFC2046" format="default">RFC 2046</xref>,
        defined requirements for the definition of new top-level types:</t>
      <blockquote>In some cases a new media type may not "fit" under any currently
        defined top-level content type. Such cases are expected to be quite
        rare. However, if such a case arises a new top-level type can be
        defined to accommodate it. Such a definition must be done via
        standards-track RFC; no other mechanism can be used to define
        additional top-level content types.</blockquote>
      <t>The 'model' top-level type was introduced by <xref target="RFC2077" format="default">RFC 2077</xref> in 1997.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC4735" format="default">RFC 4735</xref> introduced the
      'example' top-level type for use in documentation examples.</t>
      <t>The 'font' top-level media type was defined in
        <xref target="RFC8081" format="default">RFC 8081</xref>,
        a work of the 'justfont' IETF WG, in 2017.
      </t>
      <t>There is ongoing work on defining a new 'haptics' top-level media type
        in <xref target="HAPTICS" format="default">draft-ietf-mediaman-haptics</xref>.</t>
      <t>Wikipedia (at https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chemical_file_format) reports
      the unofficial use of a 'chemical' top-level type.</t>
      
      <t>The document currently defining the requirements for new top-level
        media types is <xref target="RFC6838" format="default">RFC 6838</xref>.
        Because we are trying to update what it says, we are citing the two
        relevant sections, Section 4.2.5 and Section 4.2.7, here.</t>
        <blockquote>
        <t>4.2.5.  Application Media Types</t>
          
          <t>The "application" top-level type is to be used for discrete data that
          do not fit under any of the other type names, and particularly for
          data to be processed by some type of application program.  This is
          information that must be processed by an application before it is
          viewable or usable by a user.  Expected uses for the "application"
          type name include but are not limited to file transfer, spreadsheets,
          presentations, scheduling data, and languages for "active"
          (computational) material.  (The last, in particular, can pose
          security problems that must be understood by implementors.  The
          "application/postscript" media type registration in [RFC2046]
          provides a good example of how to handle these issues.)</t>
          
          <t>For example, a meeting scheduler might define a standard
          representation for information about proposed meeting dates.  An
          intelligent user agent would use this information to conduct a dialog
          with the user, and might then send additional material based on that
          dialog.  More generally, there have been several "active" languages
          developed in which programs in a suitably specialized language are
          transported to a remote location and automatically run in the
          recipient's environment.  Such applications may be defined as
          subtypes of the "application" top-level type.</t>
          
          <t>The subtype of "application" will often either be the name or include
          part of the name of the application for which the data are intended.
          This does not mean, however, that any application program name may
          simply be used freely as a subtype of "application"; the subtype
          needs to be registered.</t>
        </blockquote>
        <blockquote>
        <t>4.2.7.  Additional Top-Level Types</t>
          
          <t>In some cases, a new media type may not "fit" under any currently
          defined top-level type names.  Such cases are expected to be quite
          rare.  However, if such a case does arise, a new type name can be
          defined to accommodate it.  Definition of a new top-level type name
          MUST be done via a Standards Track RFC; no other mechanism can be
          used to define additional type names.</t>
        </blockquote>
      <t>The two sections above are not strictly aligned, because the first says
      anything that doesn't go under a more specific type can go under the 'application'
      top-level type, while the later section allows for new top-level types.</t>
    </section>
    <section><name>Potential Criteria for New Top-Level Media Types</name>
      <t>This section describes potential criteria for new top-level media types,
        including criteria already defined in <xref target="RFC6838" format="default">RFC 6838</xref>.
        Further work is needed to distinguish between required and optional criteria.
        But it is possible that we end up with just "we didn't find any objective criteria
        for new top-level types, and we will stop looking for such criteria".</t>
      <ul>
        <li>New top level types are rare enough and different enough that each application needs to be evaluated separately.</li>
        <li>Need to be documented in a Standards Track RFC.</li>
        <li>This Standards Track RFC should include initial registrations of actual types.</li>
        <li>May (or may not) need an IETF WG for definition.</li>
        <li>Existence of a certain number of subtypes that would be grouped under the new top-level type.
        At a minimum, one actual subtype should exist. But the existence of a single subtype
        should not be enough; it should be clear that new similar types may appear in the future.</li>
        <li>Existing wide use of an undefined top-level type may be an indication of a need,
        and therefore an argument for formally defining this new top-level type.</li>
        <li>On the other hand, the use of undefined top-level types is highly discouraged.</li>
        <li>Top-level types can help humans with understading and debugging.
          Therefore, evaluating how a new top-level type helps humans understand types
          may be crucial. But as often with humans, opinions may widely differ.</li>
        <li>Top-level types are also used frequently in dispatching code.
          For example "multipart/*" is frequently handled as multipart/mixed, without understanding of a specific subtype.
          The top-level media types 'image', 'audio', and 'video' are also often handled generically.
          Documents with these top-level media types can be passed to applications handling a wide variety
          of image, audio, or video formats. HTML generating applications can select different HTML elements
          (e.g. &lt;img> or &lt;audio>) for including data of different top-level types.
          Applications can select different icons to represent unknown types in different top-level types.</li>
        <li>Need for clear criteria for what types do and don't fall under the new top-level type.</li>
        <li>Desirability for common parameters: The fact that a group of (potential) types have
        (mostly) common parameters may be an indication that these belong under a common (new) top-level type.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>There is currently no registry of top-level media types,
        but the list of top-level types available for registering subtypes
        is available at https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/media-types.xhtml.</t>
        <t>There may be a question of whether there is a need for a formal registry of
        top-level types. Such a registry might contain pointers to the definitions
        of the top-level types. As a concrete example, the author of this document
        has not yet been able to find the definition of the 'model' top-level type.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default"><name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document as such is not expected to introduce any security issues.
        The security issues of introducing a new top-level media type MUST be evaluated
        and documented carefully.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Changelog" numbered='false' toc='default'><name>Changelog</name>
      <t>RFC Editor, please remove this section before publication.</t>
      <section numbered='false'><name>Changes from draft-ietf-mediaman-toplevel-00
        to draft-ietf-mediaman-toplevel-01</name>
        <ul>
          <li>@@@@@</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section numbered='false'><name>Changes from draft-duerst-mediaman-toplevel-00
                                      to draft-ietf-mediaman-toplevel-01</name>
        <ul>
          <li>Add reference to <xref target="RFC2077" format="default">RFC 2077</xref> for definition of 'model' type.</li>
          <li>Add examples of use of top-level types for dispatch.</li>
          <li>Remove a stray '&gt;' before the mention of <xref target="RFC4735" format="default">RFC 4735</xref>.</li>
          <li>Change link to chemical/* Wikipedia page.</li>
          <li>Remove reference in abstract (pointed out by idnits).</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Continuous encouragement for writing this draft came from Harald Alvestrand.
      Further encouragement was provided by Murray S. Kucherawy. Both Harald and
      Murray also provided ideas for actual text. Without them, this memo would
      never have reached even the first draft stage.
      Alexey Melnikov provided the difficult to find pointer
      to <xref target="RFC2077" format="default">RFC 2077</xref>
      and examples for applications dispatching on top level media types.</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>


 <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="1997" month="March"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
        </reference>
 
    <reference  anchor='RFC6838' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6838'>
      <front>
        <title>Media Type Specifications and Registration Procedures</title>
        <author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='N. Freed'><organization /></author>
        <author initials='J.' surname='Klensin' fullname='J. Klensin'><organization /></author>
        <author initials='T.' surname='Hansen' fullname='T. Hansen'><organization /></author>
        <date year='2013' month='January' />
        <abstract><t>This document defines procedures for the specification and registration of media types for use in HTTP, MIME, and other Internet protocols.  This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t></abstract>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='13'/>
      <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6838'/>
      <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6838'/>
    </reference>
        

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
  
        <reference  anchor='RFC1341' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1341'>
          <front>
            <title>MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions): Mechanisms for Specifying and Describing the Format of Internet Message Bodies</title>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Borenstein' fullname='N. Borenstein'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='N. Freed'><organization /></author>
            <date year='1992' month='June' />
            <abstract><t>This document redefines the format of message bodies to allow multi-part textual and non-textual message bodies to be represented and exchanged without loss of information.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1341'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC1341'/>
        </reference>
        <reference  anchor='RFC1437' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1437'>
          <front>
            <title>The Extension of MIME Content-Types to a New Medium</title>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Borenstein' fullname='N. Borenstein'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Linimon' fullname='M. Linimon'><organization /></author>
            <date year='1993' month='April' />
            <abstract><t>This document defines one particular type of MIME data, the matter- transport/sentient-life-form type.
              This memo provides information for the Internet community.  It does not specify an Internet standard.</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1437'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC1437'/>
        </reference>
        <reference  anchor='RFC2046' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2046'>
          <front>
            <title>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types</title>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='N. Freed'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Borenstein' fullname='N. Borenstein'><organization /></author>
            <date year='1996' month='November' />
            <abstract><t>This second document defines the general structure of the MIME media typing system and defines an initial set of media types.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2046'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2046'/>
        </reference>
        <reference  anchor='RFC2048' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2048'>
          <front>
            <title>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Four: Registration Procedures</title>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='N. Freed'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Klensin' fullname='J. Klensin'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='J. Postel'><organization /></author>
            <date year='1996' month='November' />
            <abstract><t>This set of documents, collectively called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or MIME, redefines the format of messages.  This fourth document, RFC 2048, specifies various IANA registration procedures for some MIME facilities.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2048'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2048'/>
        </reference>
        <reference  anchor='RFC2077' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2077'>
          <front>
            <title>The Model Primary Content Type for Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions</title>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Nelson' fullname='S. Nelson'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Parks' fullname='C. Parks'><organization /></author>
            <author initials='Mitra' surname='' fullname='Mitra'><organization /></author>
            <date year='1997' month='January' />
            <abstract><t>The purpose of this memo is to propose an update to Internet RFC 2045 to include a new primary content-type to be known as &quot;model&quot;.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2077'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2077'/>
        </reference>
        <reference  anchor='RFC4735' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4735'>
          <front>
            <title>Example Media Types for Use in Documentation</title>
            <author initials='T.' surname='Taylor' fullname='T. Taylor'><organization /></author>
            <date year='2006' month='October' />
            <abstract><t>This document is registration for the 'example' media type and 'example' subtypes within the standards tree.  The 'example/*' and '*/example' media types are defined for documentation purposes only.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4735'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC4735'/>
        </reference>
        <reference  anchor='RFC8081' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8081'>
          <front>
            <title>The &quot;font&quot; Top-Level Media Type</title>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Lilley' fullname='C. Lilley'><organization /></author>
            <date year='2017' month='February' />
            <abstract><t>This memo serves to register and document the &quot;font&quot; top-level media type,
              under which subtypes for representation formats for fonts may be registered.
              This document also serves as a registration application for a set of intended subtypes,
              which are representative of some existing subtypes already in use, and currently registered under the &quot;application&quot; tree by their separate registrations.</t></abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='8081'/>
          <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC8081'/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor='HAPTICS' target='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-mediaman-haptics/'>
          <front>
            <title abbrev="The 'haptics' Top-level Media Type">The 'haptics' Top-level Media Type</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" status="standards" stream="IETF" value="XXXX"/>
            <author fullname="Yeshwant K. Muthusamy" surname="Muthusamy" initials="Y. K.">  
              <organization>Immersion Corporation</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Chris Ullrich" surname="Ullrich" initials="C.">
              <organization>Immersion Corporation</organization>              
            </author>
            <date/>
            <area>Internet</area>
            <workgroup>MEDIAMAN</workgroup>
            <abstract>
              <t>This memo serves to register and document the 'haptics' top-level media type,
                under which subtypes for representation formats for haptics may be registered.
                This document also serves as a registration application for a set of intended subtypes,
                which are representative of some existing subtypes already in use.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
   
 </back>
</rfc>
